Finding Aid for Laura Callow Papers, 1975-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Laura Callow Papers 1975-2013
Callow, Laura Callow, 1927-
1.5 linear feet.
Feminist, active in various women's rights organizations; biographical information files relating to involvement with ERAmerica or W.O.M.E.N. (Women Organized to Meet Existing Needs)
9960 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Laura Callow (Donor No. 8837 ) donated her papers in 1999. Additional accessions have been received.
The collection is open for research.
Laura Carter Callow (1927- ) was an activist during the 1970s and 80s who worked for the ratification of the Equal Rights Amendment on both the state and the national levels. A part-time art teacher with three children, she earned a bachelor's degree from Wayne State University. Callow was an acting officer in several women's rights organizations, and recorded a monthly spot on the "Point of View" radio program out of Detroit for almost ten years (1977 to 1986), speaking about various issues related to the ERA. Helen Milliken, whose husband was the governor of Michigan from 1969 through 1982, referred to her in a letter as "the Susan B. Anthony of Michigan."
Callow, elected president of Livonia's League of Women Voters in 1968, began her activities in the women's movement in earnest in 1972 because of discriminatory credit policies, and helped to found the Northwest Wayne County chapter of the National Organization for Women. She then became involved in Title IX (equal opportunity to women in federally-funded academic institutions) compliance issues, and later the ERA, of which she has said "ERA is about money, because most of the discrimination against women involves money." In addition to the "Point of View" broadcasts, Callow spoke at numerous conferences, meetings and classes (at high schools as well as at the University of Michigan's Law School and School of Social Work) in favor of the ERA.
Callow was sent as a delegate of the League of Women Voters in 1975 to a new coalition called W.O.M.E.N. (Women Organized to Meet Existing Needs), which brought together such state women's rights organizations as the American Association of University Women, the National Organization for Women, and the Republican Women's Caucus. She was elected secretary. In 1976, many of these same organizations, as well as W.O.M.E.N. itself and Kellogg's of Battle Creek, United Auto Workers, and Negro Business and Professional Women, joined another coalition, Michigan ERAmerica. The coalition concentrated its efforts on effecting the ratification of the ERA. Although Michigan ratified the Amendment in 1972, Michigan ERAmerica helped to keep enthusiasm up in the state, as well as to raise money for distribution to other organizations in the thirteen states that never ratified. Callow served ERAmerica as co-chair throughout the extensions granted these states and beyond; ERAmerica sent out newsletters as late as 1990.
Callow won much recognition for her efforts on behalf of the ERA and other women's issues, including receiving the Alice Paul Award from the Metropolitan Detroit area chapters of NOW, and being appointed a delegate to the Regional White House Conference on Families in 1980. She continued her correspondence with her fellow activists, including Helen Milliken and Martha Griffiths (honorary co-chairs of ERAmerica) and Elly Peterson.
The Laura Carter Callow papers document her career as an advocate for the passage of the Equal Rights Amendment and her involvement in such organizations as ERAmerica and W.O.M.E.N (Women Organized to Meet Existing Needs). The papers are divided into three series: Personal, ERAmerica and W.O.M.E.N.
Subjects:
Callow, Laura Carter, 1927-; Equal rights amendments--Michigan.; Women's rights--Michigan.; ERAmerica (Organization)--Michigan.; Women Organized to Meet Existing Needs.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Callow, Laura Carter, 1927-
Genre/Form:
Photographs
- Personal, 1976-2013
  In the Personal series are found a small folder of biographical materials, including an article and two curricula vitae; materials relating to Callow's speaking engagements not affiliated with ERAmerica or W.O.M.E.N.; and correspondence with various individuals, including Helen Milliken.
  - Awards, honorary degrees (Box 1)
  - Biographical Materials (includes photos) (Box 1)
  - Clippings (with mention of, or quote, from Laura Callow) (Box 1)
  - Conferences, speaking engagements, 1976-1982; 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1980-2005, 2008-2013,and undated, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Helen Milliken, 1978-2000 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Group photo, 1980s (Box 1)
    - Women's History Display at Livonia Public Library, 2005 (Box 1)
- ERAmerica, 1976-2013
  The ERAmerica series contains correspondence, mailings, minutes and reports from that organization, as well as transcripts and correspondence (from both the radio station--WJR--and from listeners) from Callow's "Point of View" radio broadcasts. The correspondence relates to various activities that Callow participated in on behalf of ERAmerica, including letter-writing to politicians, speaking engagements, fundraising and contributions to other organizations.
  - Coalition Updates, 1977-2009, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Conferences and Speaking Engagements
    - 1976-1999 (Box 1)
    - 2005-2013 with gaps (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1976-2013 with gaps, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Legislative
      - Michigan Legislature, 1976-1982 (Box 1)
      - Other State Legislatures, 1976-1979 (Box 1)
      - Organizations, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
    - Midland (MI)--Mary Jane Clayton, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - Member Organizations, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
    - Other Organizations, 1976-1980 (Box 1)
  - ERA Summit (position of AAUW respecting), 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Fundraising, 1977-1981 (Box 1)
  - Materials collected on ERA, arranged by state (originally in binder), 1978-1980 (Box 1)
- W.O.M.E.N. (Women Organized to Meet Existing Needs), 1975-1979
  The final series is W.O.M.E.N. This series contains correspondence, directories and minutes from 1975 through 1979.
  - Correspondence, 1975-1979 (Box 2)
  - Directories, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Minutes, 1976-1979 (Box 2)
Related Material
The Bentley Historical Library houses other collections relating to the Equal Rights Amendment movement in Michigan. These include the papers Elaine Donnelly, Martha Griffiths, Helen Milliken, Shirley Monson (photograph collection), National Organization for Women, Michigan Conference, and Elly Peterson.